So what is a dream?
First, let's define
what we are calling as dream
because the word dream
is a little too dreamy.
It's all over the place.
We're talking about dreams,
not the Martin Luther King
kind of dreams, "I have a dream,"
not that kind.
You had a dream - that kind.
You had a dream
not because you asked for it,
you had a dream in spite of yourself.
All you wanted to do was sleep,
but you had a dream.
You know the difference between "I have a dream"
and "I had a dream".
Well,
we're talking about
something that happens in your mind
or in your experience
- Let's put it this way,
it happens in your experience
when you're fast asleep.
For a whole lot of people,
their dreams are stronger experience
than their wakefulness unfortunately,
because in wakefulness
they are preoccupied with something
or the other.
In dream...
Sleep has quietened other aspects
of their physiological
and psychological activity
and the world around you.
Because of that, dream becomes
more vivid.
It's just like,
you go to a cinema theater.
You know, people are in love with film stars
more than their family
and their neighbors
and all the people that they know
in their life,
because
this is the work of the darkroom.
You must understand this.
If you play a cinema in a well-lit hall,
nobody will be impressed by those heroes.
You must switch off the light.
Once everything else is cut off
Well, you will laugh with them,
you will cry with them,
you will run away with them.
So all these things will happen
because of the darkroom.
That's what sleep is doing to you.
It's giving you a darkroom to experience
something vividly.
So this can happen
in four different ways.
There are four types of dreams.
These four types...
I'm making it four times
The yoga, the traditional yoga,
the classical yoga multiplies
this into sixteen types of dreams.
You know,
I'm a practical 21st century guru
Because of that,
I divide the numbers
and bring it down to,
all below nine.
No complex numbers, simple numbers,
because I'm talking to a rare breed
of human beings
that by the time you count
ten, they're gone.
So I'm always counting within number nine.
Having said that,
what a dream
means is something that happened
in your sleep time.
You daydreamed - that's not it.
You were fast asleep
and some experience happened.
Many might have happened
that you don't remember,
but some have happened
that you clearly remember.
Some have happened
which you partially remember.
Some have happened that you vividly remember.
Some have happened
which have left physical marks upon you.
which have manifested outside in the world.
Some have happened which can direct
or decide the very destiny of
what will happen to this being.
So among these various possibilities,
I would categorize them into four forms.
The first one is
because people are in a...
largely in a
mental diarrhea.
And this diarrhea happens
because they have invested themselves
so much, in various types of desires,
and desiring process
there is no discipline,
or
it is not a conscious desiring process.
It just happens.
Anything that they see, they desire.
Because of this,
your psychological structure
creates a defense mechanism for you.
If you pursue every desire
that arises in your life,
you're finished
You will be exhausted,
and you will die soon.
So you control yourself or
realities will not let you pursue
all those things.
Because of that,
they could play up in your mind.
Not necessarily in the same form,
in some way
random things - this person came,
that present came,
something, something, something
is happening.
Mainly
the psychological framework
is fractured
because of excessive desiring.
Because of this fractured framework,
in the daytime also they suffer these things.
But they think it's normal
because if they share with somebody
who's working in their office,
they're also in the same state
or they're in the worse state.
So it's all normal.
After all this is life.
People are saying this is life.
So desires will happen or
I'm sorry...
dreams will happen.
Because...
Because of unconscious and excessive
desiring process,
your psychological framework
is fragmented or fractured.
So, fractured dreams will happen -
random - this, this, this, this, this.
I would say...
Well, some would say...
I'm not...
I'm being too stringent.
But I would say, in my estimate,
eighty-five to ninety percent
of the dreams fall in this category.
The remaining ten - twelve percent
will fall into other three categories.
The second category of dreams may be
because of a certain depth of sleep
which most people don't get into.
If they got into a very deep sleep,
naturally,
the sleep quota would come down
- that would be an indication.
If they get into very deep states of sleep,
certain dimensions or certain aspects of
the subconscious mind may unravel itself.
Out of relaxation,
what was held may just open up,
and some insights may happen
into the individual nature of that person.
It could be
from another time in their life
of which they have no memory
but it's deep-rooted, this may come out;
or it could be from another lifetime,
it may come out.
These are all subconscious storage.
This storage
because of very deep sense of relaxation,
it may so happen
that the subconscious
opened up a little bit.
It's not that all of it will pounce out.
Just somewhere
the surface of it might have opened and
some insights
into the nature of the human being
or that individual person
may be very clear in such openings.
But I'm telling you,
of all the dreams
that people are having
on the planet,
this falls into twelve percent.
In that twelve percent,
this may account for
four, five percent, six percent maybe.
Rest is all the fractured nature
of one's psychology
which is just playing out.
The third form of dream could be,
something is building up somewhere.
Let's say we are in the
we are
in the tornado region, all right?
Right now, let's say a tornado
is just beginning.
Still, meteorological stations
have not figured it out.
It's just beginning.
Just cooking up.
See, for that kind of force to cook up,
there are factors
which are coming together slowly.
There are atmospheric factors
which are coming together
to cause
or to propel
that kind of a phenomenal force.
So they are coming together
and you are sleeping and suddenly
in your sleep
something shook in your belly,
and maybe in your dream
you had loose motions.
Not really, I'm saying.
See, I pick all the bad examples,
or something happened,
or something trembled within you
and even woke you up.
Nothing happening, everything is fine.
The tornado may be twenty-four hours,
forty-eight hours,
seventy-two hours away.
But
something happened in your dream,
and you may not be able to interpret this,
"This is a tornado,
this is a cyclone,
this is a flood,
this is an accident."
You may not be able to figure it out.
It will take some amount of training
and observation to figure it out
because in different people,
it will manifest in different forms.
These are paranormal.
That means
what's happening somewhere reflects
in your consciousness,
and you become conscious about that,
not exactly in the same form
but in some other form.
Possible.
That's another small percentage.
The fourth variety of dream
is not really a dream at all.
It is...
If you invest your life energies
into the dimension,
in your mind which we refer to as imagination...
Most human beings
because they have not
spent enough time with themselves,
their imagination is simply rolling
like a, you know, loose can.
It's just running away.
But if you pay enough attention to yourself,
if you pay attention to
what's around you, and if you imbibe
the pictures of the world
in great detail...
When I say in great detail
- if you...
this is a moving picture,
but even if it's a still picture
- if you see this flower,
if you see it in absolute detail,
and you're able to create this flower
just like this in your mind.
If you close your eyes,
you can see this flower
as clearly as you're seeing right now
with your eyes open.
Because even now you're only seeing it
in the firmament of your mind.
Your eyes may be
taking in the image,
but it is your mind which is seeing it.
So if you see it very carefully
with substantial attention...
This doesn't mean going on staring at it.
In one glance
you can see it clearly, okay?
But because
other stuff is going on,
you don't see it.
If you see it like that
and infuse your life energies in it
- that's a long way, but
if you can infuse -
you can make the flower blossom
and fragrance spread around you.
Yes.
So this is how deities are made.
This is how consecrations are done.
So this is not a dream.
But
because
nobody has found an appropriate word
for that bridge
between so-called physical reality
and what is nonphysical,
you can put it in the category of a dream
In India, this is a common thing.
People create a deity.
They work on it, work on it
and then they make her walk, literally.
You've heard of Ramakrishna
feeding the Devi, and she eats.
Food gets over.
Not imagination, not deception.
Just you infuse so much energy
into the imagination dimension
of your intelligence,
you put that much life energy,
it becomes a live... living process.
It lives with you, walks with you,
it is there with you,
more real than real.