Well,
we have just been around the United States,
touching various
Native American
nations.
One aspect
of Native American culture
or symbols
which has traveled far and wide in the world
is a dream catcher.
it's like a willow hoop
made in the form of a spider web
hanging with a few beads
and some feathers.
it is said it originates in Ojibwe
tribe or nation,
later on different versions
of the same thing reflected
in nations like Lakota, Apache, Oneida.
They came up with their own versions
of the dream catcher,
and it's gone everywhere
in the world.
In many touristy places around the world,
you will see dream catchers are being sold.
The local vendor
claiming it is from that culture.
Well, in the Ojibwe tribe,
if it was a girl child, they put
feathers from an owl;
if it is a boy child,
they put feathers from
an eagle.
Owl in these cultures
symbolized wisdom.
I don't know how that happened
because similar things
are said
probably in European cultures also.
But in India,
owl symbolizes
stupidity.
So
somehow
the tribes thought girls need wisdom,
boys need strength and courage.
Maybe they gave up on wisdom
with the male children.
To work upon something,
there must be a possibility.
So dream catchers
became popular.
Essentially, this was designed
for infants.
Well,
in India,
I think everywhere, but I will say
Southern India because I've seen this,
and I've heard people talking about it,
and I know this as a child.
Because I have this problem
of remembering
everything, inconsequential
things
that torments people around me many times.
Because I remember how you're breathing,
how you sat down, how you stood up,
how you looked, how you did not look,
everything,
from a very early age, since infancy.
When a child is born,
life enters
the fetus in a certain way,
somewhere between forty-two
to forty-eight days.
So
when life enters the fetus
which was just flesh till then
and becomes a life,
it enters through the...
the soft opening which is there in the skull
which is called as Brahmarandra.
In yoga,
a whole effort is to live there
and to leave from there;
because
birth
or infusion of life
into a piece of flesh
is not your doing,
it is the intelligence
of
creation or creator.
We want to live there
and we want to leave also from there.
So the whole effort is that
- Sahasrar.
It was amazing for me to find out
that the Native American cultures
were conscious
about
this Brahmarandra
which they refer to as the doorway
or kopavi
in their languages.
Life enters into the fetus
through this and slowly it's sealing up.
Not fully sealed
because the gestation period
is not long enough
for this closure to happen
and maybe it's not
the best thing to close it
before being born.
Because if that gets closed,
the child's skull would be too rigid
for any mother to bear a child.
So little softness of the skull
has to be retained means
the central spot is open.
The different plates are still moving around.
In Southern India...
I'm sure everywhere the midwives did this
but now qualified doctors
don't allow such things anymore,
I think.
I'm sorry if I'm saying something wrong,
because there are pediatricians here.
They're all in disguise,
so it's okay.
Midwives around the world,
I think would have done it
but in India,
they're very conscious of it.
When a child is born,
for the first few months
they shape the skull with their hands.
They will put lots of oil
and slowly shape the skull
and they'll put their fingers
inside the mouth of the child
and every day lift up this plate
so that the nose will stand out, that
it doesn't go back like this.
In our families if a grownup person comes
and he's got this kind of nose,
they'll say
what kind of mother he should have.
Somebody, an ignorant mother
who didn't do what she has to do.
They will pull up this every day
when they are giving...
washing the child.
Every day
they will put their fingers inside
with honey on their hands
so that the child doesn't
complain too much
and slowly, slowly push this up
so that this bone
will come up a little bit,
and the nose will stand out properly,
and the skull becomes reasonably round.
That means it's flexible.
So as long as it's flexible,
this is open.
Up to how many months?
A maximum of thirty months it's open.
Maximum.
But a minimum of nine to eleven months,
definitely open for everybody.
But for some children, it's
open up to thirty months.
This depends on various factors.
Let's not go into that.
So when this is open,
the child is capable - Not only
he attracted life
through this and it's already alive,
a full-fledged life.
To be born means and alive
means it is full-fledged life.
But still this child
can attract other kinds of forces.
Because this is open,
other kinds of forces or other life forms
still thinking of getting there
because the gate is open.
So one thing they do is
when they put the child to sleep,
they will tie a cloth around this.
Have you seen this?
In Southern India, villages only...
Now in hospitals, they don't allow all that.
They will tie a...
a cloth, like this a little tight,
and they will take this lamp black,
you know, carbon,
and put one big spot
somewhere.
Because when certain forces
think that gate is open and trying to go,
one thing it's blocked,
another thing is the carbon from the...
the wet carbon,
which is oily carbon,
has a tendency to draw this.
If you don't know this,
people who do occult things,
people who do this kind of sorcery
and other things,
they always smear their hands
with lamp carbon
because they want to draw them.
Well,
the young woman are putting lamp carbon
around their eyes,
because they want to draw.
Whom they draw is a different matter but...
So this as long as it's open,
there is possibility
and this possibility
will greatly be enhanced
if the child's focus
is somewhere between eighteen
to 21 inches from
their forehead.
If you have not noticed...
Those who have children must have noticed that an infant has a tendency to look here.
Have you noticed this?
Hello.
An infant, when it lies down like this,
like this, like this,
we do something, he will look here.
If you leave him alone,
the moment his focus gets to that place,
this becomes far more open.
Now gates are open with a welcome board.
So we don't want a child
to focus at eighteen to 21 inches.
We want a child to focus somewhere else.
So one thing we do is - in olden times
they took this,
you know,
coconut frond done in variety of ways
and colored in many ways
red, blue, yellow, all kinds of multi colors,
and you put it there in the...
you know,
even with the slightest breeze
it rolls,
and the child will look like that.
But that's out there,
more than twenty-four inches,
beyond 21 inches always.
Because we don't want the child
to lie there with this open
because we do not know
what will get into him.
So
we did not call it dream catcher.
It's a distractor.
We don't want the child's vision to focus
which naturally tends to focus there.
As long as this is open,
up to thirty months,
the child has a tendency to look here.
That should not happen.
He must look away.
So some colorful distraction.
Most cultures, knowingly or unknowingly,
created this distraction, isn't it?
Everywhere they created some distraction
for the child
so that he will look like this,
not just become like this.
But
people also believe that
if you don't put this,
a child will become squint-eyed
which may not be true.
But because he is looking like this,
they think he may get fixed like that.
But have you noticed this?
A child's focus, an infant's
focus is like this.
It has to become like this.
Then only has proper binocular vision
which is very vital for a grown up human being.
Well, even adult human beings,
if they want to open their Sahasrar,
we make them focus
between eighteen to 21 inches.
If this focus is maintained
in an infant,
there are many possibilities.
Sometimes very negative.
Sometimes it could work out positive,
but that's rare.
But negative things can happen in a child's life.
Child may lose its life,
but that is the least of the problems.
But child may grow into a very complex
and complicated mess
because other kinds of forces...
whether they entered or not,
they intervened
which influences this life
in a big way which some people
may never be able to shed in their entire life.
Some may grow out of it.
You will see
there are some children
who are unreasonably,
without any reason or basis,
they are simply troublesome.
They're torturous to themselves
and to everybody till
they are of four, five, six years or age,
and then after that they're quite okay.
One reason could be this,
that certain forces
influenced their kopavi
as it is called
in Native American culture, Brahmarandra
in India.
It influenced that dimension.
So that influence could last like that.
For some, it may last a lifetime.
Unless they do some serious sadhana
to get rid of it,
it may be all through their life.