I'm just
hesitating because I'm entering
dangerous territory.
People have been telling me, “Sadhguru,
this is for the exclusive.
Say whatever you want to say.” But even if
it's exclusive, there are still people,
they are not extraterrestrials.
The same people so
they just have six dollars more...
So whatever I say right
now is not for practice,
not for any kind of pursuit.
I'm just telling you simply a story.
When I play a game,
any game, I'm very deceptive.
Deceptive means how you throw the ball,
how you throw the Frisbee,
what you do, it has to be deceptive,
otherwise you don't win a game.
But when I speak, I’ve forgotten
how to be deceptive
long time ago,
so I'm struggling
how to tell you something and not tell you
everything (Laughter).
Not because it's a secret,
because
people may hurt themselves.
Okay, let's look at it this way.
Among the various
points of energy, because
dreams are very, very directly connected
to how your Pranamaya Kosha
reverberates...
How your energy functions,
that's how your thought,
that's how your emotion, that's
how your physical activity happens always.
But during waking states,
you may not allow it to happen
as it needs to happen.
You will do your own thing
according to what work you have,
what duties
you have, the social norms, everything.
You won't allow the body and mind
to work
according to your energetic intentions.
But in sleep or in dream,
it is much, much more so.
So, having said that,
there are ways to hold
your energy in a certain way
with which
one can clearly determine
what will be the nature of our dreams.
And as I said,
this will very easily fall
into the last category of dreams
which is not really a dream,
or it will become a receptive process
for the third category of dreams
which are more
paranormal in nature that your system
is responding to some other event
that is happening elsewhere.
It could be a social thing.
Anything
which is a certain amount of energy,
a certain amount of power
shift is happening.
Suddenly one can become conscious of this.
It may not be in dream alone.
It can happen in the daytime
also when you’re awake.
But in dream states,
because other disturbances
are not there, as I said, lights are off,
you know, world has disappeared.
So there is much less disturbance,
one may see it much more clearly
during dream states.
There are two different points in the body
through which one can project
one's life
energies outward when you're sleeping.
Well,
if you use your Agna
and push it out
eighteen to 21 inches,
from there if you form an equilateral...
See, let's say 21 inches away if you form
an equilateral triangle like this, you're
lying down,
you will have an equilateral triangle
with sides,
all the three sides being approximately
twenty-four inches.
So if you're here,
this will be twelve inches here
and twelve inches above.
One way,
this could be done in one's meditativeness
which is a much more saner
way of doing things.
Trying to do it in sleep states
need a certain level of
stability in the basic system.
The energetic system must be stable,
otherwise playing with
this can take you somewhere else.
But one can do it in their wakeful states.
If you are able to push your
energies out 21 inches away,
then this triangle happens.
It is because of that triangle that -
this was very clear, in India,
I don't know if you’ve seen in the Spanda
Hall images - when one is realized, one...
one kind of person has a halo...
halo here.
This is because he’s pushed his Agna out.
When we see the halo,
we know this is Pragna.
You must see the recognition
that happens when you go to certain
parts of India.
Unfortunately, rest of the world
has denied itself these things, and India
is working hard to deny itself
of everything (Laughs) right now.
In the sense,
like there are certain places
where
there is no other population
except the yogis and Sadhakas and mystics
and Aghoris and others living in certain
parts of India, still there.
A few years ago, I...
I drive into this place
and I walk in.
In one temple yard,
they're sitting.
In that there are a couple of...
two police constables and some village
officers and a few yogis are sitting.
One man is in saffron clothes.
They’re all drinking tea.
So I stand away and do namaskaram to him.
He looks at me, “Oh, you’ve come?
Please come.”
I said okay, and he said, “Please, please,
sit down, sit down.
Tea, tea,” he said.
I said okay, And then he introduces me.
He says, “He's come from South India.
He's doing a lot of work in the world.
He's spreading meditation.”
This, that, he’s telling them
everything about me
I’ve not uttered a word.
There are places like this
still where they maintain their own
atmosphere.
There used to be a lot of them
but unfortunately they’ve shrunk,
become very small.
Why I'm saying this is
because when you see the circle of Aura,
you know what is the type of dream
he is, because in that sphere of life,
your existence is seen as a dream.
See, look at it this way.
So many people were here
before us, and they’re gone.
Especially
somebody that you know was here
and now they died,
if you have lot of emotion towards them,
you won’t realize this,
but if you pay attention, just yesterday
they were walking here
- poof, gone.
After some time, you have to work hard to
imagine their face.
You have to look at their photograph,
but it's become hazier than the dream.
After some time you can talk yourself out
- actually they didn't exist,
we just thought them up.
Yes or no?
All the people,
generations of people who lived here,
did they actually exist in our experience?
No. It's like a dream.
We try to remind ourselves,
we'll try to look at their pictures
and say, “Yes, yes, they were here.”
But actually it's like a dream.
So even your existence here,
when it's seen as a dream,
this is a reality of that kind.
So if you look at a Aura
which is about twenty-four
inches in diameter,
that means it will cover Agna,
it will cover the Vishuddhi,
it will be just over the Sahasrar,
if he has this kind of plate...
You know, today is a full moon day.
So this is also something you must learn.
When you go and see the moon, don't
see it as a flat plate, white plate.
It’s a
circle.
You must see that.
It is visible if you pay enough attention,
but most people think it's a plate.
No, it's like a ball.
You have to see that
every time you see the moon because
seeing the moon in the right perspective
is very important for dreams.
Dreams and moon are very connected.
Moon always makes you little
dreamy (Laughs).
Little crazy
also because dreams are crazy.
You call something crazy
when something doesn't have logical steps.
One, two, twelve, fifteen, fifteen, three,
three, thirty-two.
If somebody reads number system like this,
you will say, “Oh, you're crazy.”
That's what dream is.
This problem of engineering
something is of the physical world.
You have to put one brick
on top of another.
In the dream, you can put the top
brick first and then put the second one.
Like this you can build the wall.
This is a dream.
So this is why, you know,
we are not letting you do Shirshasan
because,
things to do sensibly.
because, things to do sensibly.
If you can push your life energies
21 inches away
and...
I'm just saying
if you can hold it like that
just for two fortnights,
that's for one cycle of the moon,
you will get a moon around your head,
a halo, always,
which is just approximately twenty-four
inches in diameter.
It covers your face and this much.
You have seen sages and say...
If the paintings are coming
from elsewhere, it doesn't mean anything.
It may be just artists this thing.
But if it comes from India and certain
other cultures
which are conscious about this -
ancient painters, not today's painters -
then when they put the halo,
they're telling you who this man is,
what are his capabilities, what are his
inner qualifications.
Or if you push
your life energies
from your Anahata,
then it will go up to thirty-three
inches, anywhere
between thirty to thirty-three inches.
If that happens,
the base of the triangle will become
approximately thirty-nine inches.
That is, the sides of the triangle
will be thirty-nine inches
for a equilateral triangle.
The significance of this is
this will cover all the seven
major chakras - this triangle.
Now you have seen some yogis have a halo.
If they're sitting here,
they have a halo like this.
Have you noticed this?
No? You've not seeing such paintings?
Nothing here?
What did they give to Adiyogi (Laughs)?
No halo. That's good.
They didn't see it.
So you will see some yogis,
a halo is going like this.
This is a thirty-nine-inch diameter.
Doesn’t matter what’s your height,
this is a thirty-nine-inch diameter
halo.
That means it covers all the aspects.
If you’re able to do both in your sleep,
that you're able
to push your Agna out 21 inches and this,
then these two triangles
will intersect and the intersection
will cover the Vishuddhi
in a powerful way.
Now, when such a thing happens,
normally in India we say
he is an incarnation of Shiva
because
the energy...
What a halo is, is,
is a nurturing bubble
that you carry with yourself.
Either just your head is being nurtured
or your whole thing is being nurtured
and particular focus on Vishuddhi.
If everything is being nurtured
and particular focus on Vishuddhi,
then we say, “You’re
just like him.”
Now, if...
if you manage to push this approximately,
let's say,
not 21 inches, you pushed it nine inches.
Then what happens to you is,
you will have relief from constant
unnecessary mental activity.
This is what
a whole lot of people in the world
are saying are the benefits of meditation,
that their mental activity has come down,
they’re feeling little more peaceful
and they're little better human beings
because
in their daytime,
knowingly
or unknowingly, little has been pushed.
May not be happening in sleep,
but if it happens in sleep, you will find
complete relief from this unnecessary
mental activity that's happening.
If you manage to push this,
let's say, twelve inches,
very easily you access the minds
of...
minds
and intentions of all the people
who are connected with you.
Particularly if they’re blood related,
you can very easily know their intent
and their minds,
effortlessly, without trying to read their
minds, simply like that.
If you push this out
fifteen inches, you will know
of significant events anywhere
that's happening.
Major shifts that happened in this planet
or in this planetary system,
you will know.
It is from this
that you will see
many yogis and sages and seers predicted
that at this time, a comet will happen,
a major comet will happen which can cause
this kind of influence upon the planet.
Like this, they have said in the past
and it's happened exactly at those times
because they saw it coming,
not with a telescope or something,
in their energies they saw it's coming.
If you push this eighteen inches,
all that's worth knowing you can access.
Takes a little...
like going to a library
and reading up a bit,
but you have access
to all that’s worth knowing.
If you
push it full 21 inches and it stays there,
then your consciousness becomes cosmic
and can facilitate liberation or
what is now generally known
as Mahasamadhi or
Mahaparinirvana.
That means one can leave consciously.
If you can hold it up at 21 inches
away from your Agna,
this will open up slowly.
As it opens up, life
and leaving the body becomes an entirely
conscious process.