Dreams and impact of dreams
have been studied
and analyzed and brutalized
and mutilated by every culture
because they're looking at it from outside.
In modern times, in 20th century,
modern science
has tried to analyze dreams,
and they have been the people
who've been most off the mark.
Ancient societies, tribal societies
have figured some aspects of it
which are quite accurate.
Some aspects of it
made up out of fear and hope and
in search of power and access.
Distortions have happened,
but they have some sense about
these things
because they've paid attention
to their own dreams.
But this idea that you can catch a dream,
is very romantic,
but is it realistically possible?
Yes, it is possible.
Not because of the willow hoop,
but it's possible to capture a dream.
Few days ago, we were at Memphis
where the famous statement by
Dr. Martin Luther King -
"Yes, I have a dream".
Well, that is not
a dream that he had in his sleep.
It is a dream that he envisioned.
It's a desire
that was empowered
to make it into a reality.
What is a dream, what is reality
- the line is thin,
very thin.
So one must tread this terrain
very consciously,
very carefully, because...
this has happened to me.
I'm...
I'm little thick in the head, you know?
I don't learn anything from anywhere,
I learn everything by experience.
Well, fortunately
the experience has been expansive,
so it saved me. If it was not,
I would be in a lot of trouble.
So this happens.
If you're running on a land
which has lot of either
rat holes or rabbit holes...
Just now we went into such terrain.
We were in Mojave Desert.
These...
They are called prairie dogs or whatever,
small this big animals
which look like half rats half squirrels.
They call them prairie dogs here.
In other parts of the world
with slight differences
they're called by different names.
In India, it's largely
rabbit holes and bandicoots making holes.
So if you run hard on these fields,
suddenly your leg could get trapped
in one of these holes.
And when you're running full speed
if suddenly one ankle
or one foot is held,
then you yank it so hard,
you will break your...
usually your ankle or your foot.
Well,
as by now it is a...
it is known to lot of people.
when I was running hard
trying to catch something,
one foot got stuck in the hole,
and I yanked it, and it broke.
I broke my left ankle
eleven times, right one nine times.
Still, functional.
This one, see I'm saving it.
Not every time I stuck it into a rabbit hole.
I did it only once.
Every time I broke it a different way.
Once with a rabbit hole,
once flying hang gliders,
maybe twice playing hockey.
Like this in different ways.
There are many ways to break your bones.
So
when you walk this terrain
of dream
and consciousness,
it's a terrain with lots of holes.
You must be very nimble
to travel such a terrain,
otherwise your foot will get stuck
in one of those
empty holes of hallucination,
and something will break.
This...
This warning I think
would be everywhere in every culture.
But you know,
warning signs are written to be ignored
- because most human beings
ignore the warning signs.
I think the only culture
which has tried to tread this terrain
without any warning signs, thinking it's
some exotic, romantic way of doing things
is the European culture.
European psychiatry
and psychiatrists
have tried to traverse this terrain
without any breaks, without any warnings.
I think they've paid the price for that also
because they're analyzing
everything from somebody's experience.
They are not delving into
their own experience.
They have no clue about that.
They made all the wrong conclusions, I would say.
The two famous names
are very holy for today's societies
- I can't touch them
but I'll just mention them
with namaskar
- well, Sigmund Freud and Carl Jung are the big two
in this field,
and both of them
could not agree with each other.
They constantly
debated and fought and argued about this.
Well,
I don't want to go into that discussion
because
it is too off the mark.
See, if you tell me
your dream...
You can never tell me
your dream in its entirety
with all its full manifestations.
Why a dream?
You just walk down
the Isha lane here for five minutes
and tell me everything
that you saw exactly.
Unless you're so preoccupied,
you don't see a damn thing.
Nobody can describe what they saw in
five minutes
on the Isha lane which both sides are trees,
no traffic, no people,
no great events happening there,
but still you can never tell anybody
exactly what you saw.
So when you throw
a few bits of what you saw,
and I analyze that,
and I come to my own conclusions
about it,
based on that conclusions
I will make conclusions
about every other human being
- this is completely out of place.
But other ancient cultures
have looked at it
from one's own experience.
Some had the necessary insights,
some lost their way here
and there because, as I said,
the holes in the terrain are too many
and people get stuck
in those empty holes.
Across human history,
this has been studied by
sages, astrologers, intellectuals
and suburban garden mystics.
Every kind of people have tried to
give meaning, interpretations
and examine the possibilities of what
a dream is
and what it could be saying,
or what it could be trying to say,
or what it absolutely signifies.
Like this, different people
with different levels of certainty
or uncertainty have gone at it.
For most people, they are
right fifty percent of the time.
You know, it's easy
to be right fifty percent of the time.
It's as easy as flipping a coin.
Fifty percent of the time you'll always be right.
I mean to say, most of the time,
there might have been small insights
but largely guesswork.
Many cultures
have seen dreams as prophetic
and supernatural,
many have seen dreams
as spiritual message.
Many have seen dreams as
God talking to them.
Many have used dreams
to drive themselves crazy, lose their
sanity.
Repetitive dreams of the same kind,
many times
have driven people off their sanity.
Ancient Egyptian cultures
always believed
dreams have a significant impact
on the waking reality
and dreams cure illnesses,
make important decisions.
Both
personal and political
decisions were made based on dreams.
The Egyptians also saw dream
as a possibility
to travel beyond
the physical body.
There are paintings which are over 5000 years old
which show that
when a person is lying down and dreaming,
the spirit, or the soul,
or the being is outside the body
traveling,
or so is the interpretation.
These are western interpretations.
I will come to this later,
why this is so.
There is also a book
in the Egyptian culture called the Dream book,
which was written around 12000 BC
during the time of Ramses.
In dreams, Egyptians believed...
The book goes about talking about
how gods demand
what they want,
what sacrifices they want from you
and warn you of danger.
Dream is a deal time.
You can close the deal in the dream.
And because people saw...
either they saw or they claimed
they saw something,
it has happened in many cultures,
living people have been butchered.
Because in my dream, I saw
this Justin had two horns,
so I knew he's
the manifestation of devil.
And next day morning, I get up and say,
"He's the devil.
I saw him in my dream."
Well, he will be lynched or butchered.
This has happened
many, many, many times
in various cultures.
So this is why I'm saying
we must proceed into this terrain very, very carefully
because there are too many empty holes
where you could get stuck.
Even Hippocrates who is considered
as the father of modern medicine,
linked dream
to one's health and well-being.
Well, these ancient texts
and ancient dialogues,
how they've been translated
and how they've been interpreted
is always a questionable thing.
I don't like to blame the people
who are not here today,
who are gone long time ago,
for the understanding or misunderstanding
of today's generation,
about what they could have done or what
they could have thought
or what they could have dreamed, even worse.
So working with dreams
with all kinds of misconceptions,
working with dreams with dreams
about dreams
is not a good idea.
If you want to work with dreams,
you should not have any dreams about dreams.
You must be very clear
about what it is
and how it functions within you.
By analyzing somebody else's
dreams, you will never know this.
You must know the mechanism
which makes this happen.
It's not about a dream.
It is not about a thought.
It is not about an emotion.
It's not about a life's experience.
It is about the mechanism
that creates all this.
Only because you're here,
there is a thought,
there is an emotion, there is a dream,
there is an idea,
there is a philosophy,
there are belief systems.
Everything is possible
because there is a mechanism.
It's about how you use it.
Instead of understanding
the mechanism,
people are trying to understand
the consequences.
By
reading the footprint of a man,
the only thing you could know
is the size of his foot.
You will not know anything else.
Maybe his weight also you can assess.
You cannot even assess his height.
There can be somebody
very short with big feet.
You can probably assess his weight
depending on the imprint.
Beyond that, there is nothing.
But if you were a dog...
No, I'm not saying this
in any derogatory way.
I'm talking about a higher grade of senses.
If you were a dog,
you know something about him,
you know he's our neighbor,
but that's about it.
So similarly, dreams are footprints.
By footprint,
you can know a few things.
Doesn't reveal the nature of the being.
Doesn't reveal the nature
of anything for that matter, gives you a
small scent of something.
Don't go after that scent
because you don't have
the sense of a dog.
If you go after that scent,
it's an endless thing. Then
one day you see that
you're not dreaming enough,
then you will go on a hallucinogenic
because you want to dream
endlessly, lucidly.
When people
are under the influence of alcohol also,
but more so under various hallucinogenic chemicals,
people dream like crazy.
More real than real.
Means nothing.