Every culture has invested
a certain amount of energy
and a certain amount of attention
and certain significance
to dreams.
Native American traditions
have invested
some amount of focus on dreams.
They see it as an extension of reality
which is not all wrong.
They seek practical and spiritual guidance
which may not be all wrong.
I'm saying this
because they are deeply involved in
occult processes.
We have seen the powerhouse of Mato Tipila
which is of Vishuddhi.
People who are empowered by that,
in a way,
they transact between
life and death,
dream and wakefulness
a little more easily.
They talk about dream as a connection
between
physical and spiritual world.
Not entirely wrong.
That depends on
what you call as spiritual.
Right now, there is so much imagery
behind me in the form of these murals.
Well, if
you look at these images -
you must understand
these images are of a certain culture,
of a certain tradition,
which points towards spirituality.
It is not spirituality per se.
If you go at what is spiritual,
purely spiritual,
then all this, not necessary.
But you need inspiration.
You need to handle your psychological
and emotional
turmoils that go on within you.
If you’re still there,
then you need this tradition.
You need this culture to support you,
to remind yourself of people who...
how they transcended these
impediments within themselves
and how they rendered themselves
to higher possibilities.
In that sense, as a process,
as a larger process,
yes, it is true.
Dream and spirituality
- there is.
But one who
strives to become absolutely
conscious or aware,
for that
person
all these things are irrelevant.
Irrelevant.
Well, Shiva, Sati, Parvati,
this, that, their dance, their this thing
and the drama around them
not relevant for a person
who is purely conscious.
But very relevant for somebody who’s still
trying to...
not scale some other height
but trying to get across their own
physiological
and psychological impediments
- very, very relevant.
So in that context, dream
and spiritual dimension
have a relationship and dreams could have
consequences
in how one’s
psychological structure shapes up.
Because of that, it could in
turn have impact
on how one's physical life
takes shape,
very possible.
But dreams are not messages
coming from somewhere.
It is about
your un-blossomed intelligence
trying to figure things out,
trying to touch dimensions
which are not in your experience.
Well,
if you consciously seek those things
or if you try to induce these things,
dreams,
if you bring lucidness to your dream
using chemicals or -
because in this country,
you have to spell it out
chemicals or herbs or weeds or
buds or stems or roots (Laughter)
or the bark of a tree (Laughter),
I don't know.
Or a toad's back legs (Laughter).
If you're using any of them,
then you could be on a ride forever
not knowing which is which
because you just woke up
and sunlight
fell upon you, you're also feeling good
today.
Everything...
All your faculties are at their best.
If now you can't see what you need to see,
you seeing when you're exhausted,
when you're fast asleep and exploring
dimensions of consciousness
or dimensions of reality or mysticism
in a state of exhaustion
and unconsciousness,
well, I can't say too
much because too many people are involved
(Laughs).
Well, I would just say all the best.
I hope you have a long life
because you will need a very long life.
The Native American people
also have a term called Dream Walker.
One who can control their dreams
or some kind of play, a liaison
between physical and metaphysical worlds,
they took the services
of powerful dreamers
during dead winter when food was scarce.
Because these are hunting and gathering
tribes,
in winter times
finding food is a challenge
so they hired or employed
strong dreamers who could dream
where the hunt is.
Fifty percent of the time they're right.
But above all, a human being is capable
of developing a sense
to where something is,
simply by being a little more conscious,
which they might have done.
People
might have thought he's dreaming it up.
Maybe he had a little extra sense
that he could figure out certain movement
and he's able to say that.
I must tell you, in India
there are snake
charmers (Laughs), even today.
They live around the yoga center,
a whole tribe of them.
You call that guy,
he will come, in one afternoon,
you tell him in this area
whatever snakes are there, clean it up.
He will go sit in one place
and start mumbling (Laughs)...
You know,
I'm talking about this
because I've been humiliated by these guys
(Few laugh).
Because
I've been
meddling with snakes
since I’m six, seven years of age,
and I could walk into the forest
and smell it out
and figure it out where the cobras are.
I would exactly know under
which rock it is, and I would pull it out.
But I have to go in search of them.
I have to go,
look for signs in the land
if they have moved or smell
and figure it out.
Well,
I would say
when I thought it's here,
at least sixty percent of the time,
I was always right.
I'm saying a little more
than a flip of a coin.
Not guesswork. This is a calculation.
This smell, this thing and this hole,
this, this, this - he must be here.
But forty percent of the time he is
not there.
He's gone somewhere else.
But this guy just come and sits there
and starts mumbling something.
I don't know what the hell he mumbles
and snakes cannot hear.
You know that. They’re stone deaf.
But in an afternoon
he will catch twenty-five snakes.
They'll all come.
When I sat silently
meditating, they came,
but they came out of their sense.
I didn't know why they came.
I couldn't make them come.
They came looking for me.
But he makes them come.
And the guy, if you give him
twenty-five rupees, fifty rupees, he's
happy and he’ll take it and go.
This guy.
So I felt humiliated that (Laughs)
I have to go
put my hand under the rocks
and search out risking a bite.
But this guy just sits there
and mumbles around.
It all comes to him.
And snakes are stone deaf,
so they can't hear his mumbling.
Maybe he's just mumbling and bumbling
to just set himself
into some space,
but they'll come for him.
Maybe there were people like that
in the tribes
that they knew where the buffalo is or
the buffalo came for them, we don't know.
Possible.
But all these things are put under dream,
they're being called Dream Walkers.
I wouldn't put this under dream,
but I think in these cultures
we don't know what local words they had.
But when western interpreters came,
anything that they cannot perceive,
they cannot logically think through,
probably
they put it all this under dream category.
So there are many rituals which create
dream-like
altered states of consciousness.
There are vision quests
which involve prolonged
fasting, drum beating, dancing,
flesh sacrifices
and of course, certain plants
like Peyote, Ayahuasca,
and the famous Sun Dance.
All this created
a dream-like situation.
Probably
when somebody loses a little
control
over their normal sense of logic,
that could be considered a dream.
I wouldn't say it's totally wrong.
But I don't think
today in the population, in the societies,
people understand dream in that context.