Is there a way to do lucid dreaming,
where
as I fall
asleep and shift into a dream state,
I still retain awareness?
Well,
that's only where you wish to fly,
it's up to you,
but I want you to understand that
the word dream means it's not real.
That's what the word dream
or the word Swapna means
it's not real.
A whole lot of people, especially children,
children between,
I would say, eight to fourteen years of age,
have a tendency to do this
that some of these children dream
very strong when they're awake.
Has it happened to you
when you were that age?
When eight
to fourteen years of age,
when your intelligence is blossoming,
but you're not yet
hijacked by your hormones,
there is a strong tendency to dream strong.
A child will simply sit like this, and
if he reads a story or
sees a movie or something else
somebody told him,
he will just
create a reality with that.
Well,
this can...
you know, I've seen this with children,
and I've
made efforts to disturb that dream
always
because
this can...
First of all, we need to understand this mechanism
is so subtle.
Anything that subtle
it robust also but
anything that is subtle
always has a certain sense
of fragility attached to it.
So we must understand
our sanity,
for every one of us
I'm saying, our sanity is not a guarantee.
Like your health is not a guarantee.
Just because
you're eating proper food,
you're doing the right thing,
it doesn't mean
for your life you will be healthy.
Yes, largely we can take care,
but there is no guarantee.
People who are doing everything right,
get unhealthy,
get all kinds of diseases.
So, similarly,
your sanity is not an assured
dimension of life.
It needs to be kept carefully.
One must guard
to ensure
that we don't go off,
into that.
So,
giving too much significance
to dream and making it
more and more real in your experience
is like pushing the line of sanity.
Well, you may not cross,
but there's no guarantee you will not.
You could.
Many people do.
You must understand this...
I've seen,
you know, some of my... during...
when I was a youth,
boys who are around
me were normal,
perfectly normal in every way.
Suddenly after three months, the guy has gone crazy.
In six months he commits suicide. He dies.
Perfectly normal guy.
He has no great issues in his life,
nothing, the usual things, whatever
young people, but nothing.
There are no drugs,
there is no alcohol, there is no anything.
But perfectly normal person
when he flips into insanity,
you don't know,
because
it's a very fragile privilege
that you have
to be perfectly sane
in every given situation.
There are people who are sane
when situations are sane,
if situation goes little crazy,
they will all go crazy.
There's a whole lot of people like that.
You just have to...
You know that snake around Adiyogi?
If it comes alive and just comes here,
you will see how many people are crazy,
how many people are sane
Hello? Lucid dream
So if outside situations go off
the track,
you will also go off
because
sanity is a very fragile privilege.
We must hold it on
as a very precious, valuable privilege.
Because
once you lose it,
we've lost all our faculties
everything that we have, we've lost.
So
this lucid dreaming
and, you know, you can fly,
you can become this, you can become that,
well, comes from the Native American culture.
It's all over the place today in America.
A whole lot of people are doing
other kinds of plants, herbs,
herbs,
stuff, roots, box, whatever
to get lucid dreams.
I would say don't.
But you can't stop
people from dreaming.
I have a dream.
Yes, I have a dream.
Now,
if
dreams are becoming like reality,
you must watch out,
because one day
you will not know the distinction.
One day when you do not know the distinction,
people will experience you as insane.
You may think you're perfectly fine,
but the world
will experience you as insane.
This has happened
to a lot of people
on the spiritual path
also.
Without doing any drugs,
without doing any chemicals, nothing.
Simply
devotees drive themselves up.
We are
doing devotion here
in a controlled, stable way.
It's very important.
We are not doing boom
kind of devotion
which exists in India as a cult,
that they are like
fantastic people,
but they're crazy.
They will not do anything
effectively in their life,
but
like this
if they sit like this only
no drug,
nothing, simply
because lucid dreams.
And once
there is not enough stability in your energy system,
if dream becomes too strong,
then you will know no distinction
between
what is eyes open, what is eyes closed.
This distinction
is very important
eyes open, eyes closed.
This distinction you must check.
If this distinction is becoming thin,
you must know
your line of sanity is very thin,
very thin.
So
the simple thing that everybody could do is...
See, if you can just
lie down on your back
for most part of the night.
Simple.
That much practice you do.
With the Sadhana...
If you're doing enough yogic Sadhana,
slowly
these things may evolve by itself.
Well,
not everybody
may be able to lie down flat on their back
for the entire night.
But in my opinion, you should not be sleeping
Sunset to sunrise is twelve hours.
A third of that is okay.
A little more is okay
but not entire night. If you're doing enough
Sadhana,
if you lie down on your back,
then you will see
the problem
is actually the pillow
and your... maybe your bum.
Two bumps, one here, one there.
So if
pillow is
you notice is the problem, reduce it, reduce it.
See if you can get rid of it.
That's the best thing.
About
the shape of your body,
all you have to do is,
depending upon the shape of your body,
accordingly
you must adjust the angle of your legs.
If you adjust the angle of your legs,
the enhancement of body in certain ways
that is naturally there
will be adjusted,
and you can sleep on your back.
if you do this
consciously
at least for half the time that you sleep...
Well,
you may achieve at least dreamless sleeps
which is a good thing.
It's called Sushupti,
that means your...
your sleep is such
there is no rem,
there is no dream,
there is simply
Every day you may not sleep like that.
Some days
some disturbances may happen,
something may be happening somewhere,
something may... might have happened in your life.
Something may happen, but
there is no need for anybody to go to bed
every day and every day have dreams.
That means you're not in a very
healthy condition.
You're not in a good place.
Once in a way some dream came,
it doesn't matter.
You don't have to give too much meaning to it.
But every day if you're dreaming,
one simple thing to do
is this
that you lie down flat on your back and sleep.
You will see
you will breathe better.
That means the life will happen better
in the system
and all organs will work better.
And also ensuring
if you don't want to have
unnecessary
dream's disturbances,
you must eat at least four hours before you go to bed
minimum.
Five to six hours is good.
That is
you are almost hungry
before you go to bed,
you just drink a glass of water
and go to bed.
Wow,
you'll wake up early in the morning
No dreams.
Simply sleep and wake up